Guide to the Committee of 100 on the Federal City records [Part II], 1909-1996 MS2131
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Committee of 100 on the Federal City records [Part II]
1909-1996
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Committee of 100 on the Federal City (Washington, D.C.)
MS2131
11.5 Linear Feet
Collection documents the Committee's stance on the issues it chose to address within the areas of planning, historic preservation and transportation. Within the subject of transportation there are enough files to detail many of the various highway and rapid transit projects the Committee of 100 dealt with. The collection also has files dealing with zoning regulations, housing, urban design and city water resources.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Historical or Biographical Note
The mission of the Committee of 100 on the Federal City is to safeguard and advance the fundamental planning, environmental and aesthetic values inherited from the L'Enfant Plan and the McMillan Commission that give Washington its historic distinction, natural beauty and overall livability. The Committee advances the proposition that planning of the highest caliber is essential to ensure for residents of Washington D.C. - indeed for all the citizens of the United States for whom the Nation's Capital is a symbol - the attainment and preservation of a city worthy of the Nation. From specific proposals such as its plan for the redesign of the Whitehurst Freeway below Georgetown, to more general initiatives, such as testimony on regional air quality standards and support for reinvigorating of the NCPC, the Committee continues its broad campaign for exemplary planning in the Nation's Capital. The Committee is engaging in close consultation on planning issues with the Congress and the District of Columbia Government. The Committee has also established its own ad hoc subcommittee on regional planning to work in liaison with kindred organizations in Maryland and Virginia.
The Committee of 100 on the federal City was organized in 1923 by the American Planning and Civic Association (APCA) in order to study the problems facing the Nation's capital. Frederic A. Delano, Uncle to President Franklin Delano Roosevelt, was the first Chairman of the Committee. Following its conception, the Committee of 100 has served as a citizens forum discussing planning issues that confront the District. The Committee separated itself from the APCA in 1965 and incorporated as a non-profit organization.
For over half a century, the Committee has attracted to its membership architects, planners, landscape architects, lawyers, conservationists, historians, and concerned citizens from diverse professions and backgrounds. It has sought to rally national, regional, and local organizations which share in the mission of safeguarding the heritage of Washington, D.C. Not only is the Committee of 100 on the Federal City the oldest planning body and the oldest citizens' forum on planning issues in the Nation's Capital, it is also one of the most effective and vigorous organizations of its kind.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains articles, minutes, correspondence, financial statements, and reports. These materials date from 1909-96 with the bulk of the material falling within the dates 1980-94. The material in this collection document the Committee's stance on the issues it chose to address within the areas of planning, historic preservation and transportation. Within the subject of transportation there are enough files to detail many of the various highway and rapid transit projects the Committee of 100 dealt with. The collection also has files dealing with zoning regulations, housing, urban design and city water resources.
The original donation from the Committee of 100 to The George Washington University was in 1986. Additional donations were made in 1989, 1991, 1995 and 1997.
Collection Organization
Organized into two series: General files and Subcommittee files.
Washington (D.C.); Height restrictions; Buildings; Housing; Roads; Automobile parking; City planning; Local transit; Zoning; Parks; Regional planning; Water-supply; Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority; Committee of 100 on the Federal City (Washington, D.C.); American Planning and Civic Association
- General files, 1938-1996; MS2131 Series 1; 4 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 7, Box 6, Box 8, Box 3, Box 2, Box 5, Box 4)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains by-laws, addresses, reports, financial statements, resolutions, minutes, newspaper articles, publications, and photographs. This material dates from 1938-96.
  - General files, undated (Box 1)
    General note
  - By-Laws, photocopy of Committee of 100's By-Laws, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - By-Laws, photocopies of a report, a piece of correspondence and changes to bylaws, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - By-Laws, photocopy of page 1976 of D.C. Code, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - By-Laws, as amended as of December 31, 1981, 12/31/1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Resolutions, opposition to PR 8-531, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Resolutions, regarding the memorial for Women in the Military, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Address, made by Frederic A. Delano about a plan for a comprehensive system of parks, parkways, playgrounds, community centers and other recreational activities in Washington D.C., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Statement, made by Reginald W. Griffith on the Department of Transportations proposed policy for Washington's airports, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Statement, prepared by the Committee of 100 on the Environmental Element of the Comprehensive Plan, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Statement, made before the city council of Washington D.C., 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Statement, of the Trustees of the Committee of 100 on the Master Plan for the Federal Triangle, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Statement, prepared by the Committee of 100 on Metro Green Line, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Statement, prepared by the Committee of 100 on Ward Plans Amendment Act, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Testimony, before the zoning commission of the District of Columbia on case 89-19C, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Statement, prepared by the Committee of 100 on Proposed Whitehurst Freeway, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Statement, prepared by the Committee of 100 concerning exceptions to building lot control, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Statement, prepared by the Committee of 100 on the comprehensive plan review resolution, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Testimony, presented before the Historic Preservation Review Board in support of landmark designation for Hillandale, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Statement, prepared by the Committee of 100 regarding the Schedule of Heights Amendment Act, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Statement, summary of statement prepared by the Committee of 100 concerning Zoning Commission case number 91-8, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Statement, of the Committee of 100 on proposed demolition of historic building in Washington Navy Yard, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Statement, made by Richard Longstreth concerning the preservation of the Victor building, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Statement, before the National Capital Planning Commission concerning the NBC Tower, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Statement, on the Municipal Fish Wharf, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Statements, concerning the Redskins stadium, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Testimony, concerning the former Garfinckel's Spring Valley Store, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Testimony, presented on behalf of the Committee of 100 concerning the proposed alterations to the Hecht Company Building, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Statement, prepared by the Committee of 100 on the Amendment Process for the District Elements of the Comprehensive Plan, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Reports, response to the General Accounting Office made by the Committee of 100 concerning a study of the National Capital Planning Commission, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Reports, made to the Council of the District of Columbia concerning the closing of an alley on 13th and 14th streets, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Reports, presented to the District of Columbia Department of Public Works and National Park Service concerning the Barney Circle Freeway Project, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Financial Statements, treasurer's end of year report, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Financial Statements, treasurer's end of year report, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Financial Statements, treasurer's end of year report, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Financial Statements, treasurer's end of year report, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Financial Statements, treasurer's end of year report, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Financial Statements, treasurer's end of year report, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Financial Statements, treasurer's end of year report, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Financial Statements, treasurer's end of year report, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Financial Statements, treasurer's end of year report, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Financial Statements, treasurer's end of year report, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - General files, undated (Box 2)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the Trustee's meetings, includes a list of members, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the Trustee's meetings, includes a list of members, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and that of the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the Trustee's meetings, includes a list of members, correspondence, clippings and the treasurer's report, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and that of the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and that of the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and that of the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and that of the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General files, undated (Box 3)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and that of the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and that of the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and that of the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and that of the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Meetings Files, minutes and files related to the meetings of all members and the Trustees, includes a list of members, correspondence and clippings, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - General files, undated (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, to and from the U. S. Treasury Department, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, from Elizabeth Rowe to Mrs. Keith Cannan inviting her to be a member of the Committee, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, to and from Committee members, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, to and from Committee members, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, to and from Committee members, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, from the Chairman of the Committee of 100 to the Zoning Commission of D.C., 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, from the Chairman of the Committee of 100 to the National Capital Planning Commission, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, to Marion S. Barry, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, to and from the Committee of 100 about the Redskins Stadium, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, to and from Committee members, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, regarding zoning issues in relation to the Theodore Roosevelt Bridge, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, to and from Committee members, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, to and from Committee members, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, to and from the Committee of 100 about the Redskins Stadium, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, to and from Committee members, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, to and from President McGrath about zoning for 1150 K Street and other issues, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, to and from Committee members, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, to and from President McGrath regarding the National Museum of the American Indian, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, to and from Committee members, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - General files, undated (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, to and from Committee members, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, to and from Committee members, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, to and from Committee members, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - General files, undated (Box 6)
  - History Files, historical notes and other files, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - History Files, membership prospect biographical files, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - History Files, timeline and historical notes about the National Capital Planning Commissions' transportation planning history for time period, 1926-1985 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - History Files, Historical notes about the archives collection and the committee as a whole, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - History Files, Comments on the Heritage Report (Heritage Report is missing), 1990 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - History Files, Two page history, 1990 ca. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - History Files, The Committee of 100 on the Federal City: Its History and Its Service to the Nation's Capital by Richard Striner, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - History Files, biographical files of members, 1994-1996 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - History Files, exhibit and event files related to the exhibit and event - A Capital Commitment, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - History Files, draft summary of the exhibit and event A Capital Commitment, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - History Files, old letterhead and envelopes, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Articles and Clippings, photocopy of clipping with a photo of the Evans building, 1909 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Articles and Clippings, various clippings on various topics affecting the Nation's Capital, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Hillandale development, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Washington D.C. area airports, 1980-1984 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Articles and Clippings, about water and sewage issues, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Metro, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Rock Creek and transportation, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Metro, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Metro, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Metro bus lines garage site, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Metro Green Line, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Redskins Stadium, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Articles and Clippings, about George Washington Parkway, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the CSX Georgetown Spur, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the Barney Circle road project, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the D.C. Prison Site, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Techworld, 1986-1995 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Articles and Clippings, one copy of the February issue of the DC Gazette, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the proposed Judiciary Office building, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Redskins Stadium, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the Anacostia Inner Harbor, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the Potomac Greens, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - General files, undated (Box 7)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the Cleveland Park-Park and Shop, 1987-1991 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the Capital Crescent Park, 1987-1993 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the National Capital Planning Commission call to expand, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Redskins Stadium, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Airport noise, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Urban Planning and Preservation in the nation's capital, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Market Square North, 1988-1991 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Articles and Clippings, about PortAmerica, 1988-1994 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Woodland-Normanstone Subdivision, 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the Washington By-Pass proposals, 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Articles and Clippings, about downtown development, 1989-1993 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Articles and Clippings, about housing downtown, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the real estate industry, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the D.C. Nozzle law, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Redskins Stadium, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the Church of Christ Science building near DuPont Circle, 1990-1993 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the Archibold Cabin, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the McMillan Park Reservoir, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the Glover-Archibold Parkway and transportation, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the Greyhound bus depot building, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Articles and Clippings, about North Union Square, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Redskins Stadium, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Articles and Clippings, about 2500 Pennsylvania Avenue, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Articles and Clippings, about a memorial for Women in the Military, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Articles and Clippings, about 7th Street Corridor, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Articles and Clippings, about transportation management and clean air, 1991-1994 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Redskins Stadium, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Logan Circle, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Articles and Clippings, about historic building at the Navy Yard, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Articles and Clippings, about transportation regional planning alternative, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the Municipal Fish Wharf, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the Barney Circle road project, 1992-1993 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the Georgetown University power plant, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Redskins Stadium, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Articles and Clippings, about WETA, 1993-1994 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Articles and Clippings, about DisneyAmerica theme park, 1993-1994 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the 14th Street Trolley, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the New York Avenue Corridor, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the Old Eastern Market, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Redskins Stadium, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Articles and Clippings, about DisneyAmerica theme park, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the George Washington University Health and Wellness Center, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Articles and Clippings, about Redskins Stadium, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the Decatur House, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Articles and Clippings, about the Silver Spring Mega Mall, 1995-1996 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - General files, undated (Box 8)
  - Publications, Committee of 100 newsletter, "Occasional Paper", 11/1995 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Publications, Committee of 100 newsletter, "Occasional Paper", 06/1996 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, of the D.C. Prison site, 1987 ca. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, of the Woodland-Normanstone Development, 1989-1990 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, of the Church of Christ Science building, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, of the National Broadcasting Company's Tower near the George Washington University Campus, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Subcommittee files, 1967-1996; MS2131 Series 2; 7.5 Linear feet (Box 9, Box 10, Box 22, Box 23, Box 19, Box 18, Box 21, Box 20, Box 16, Box 15, Box 17, Box 12, Box 11, Box 14, Box 13)
  This series contains articles, correspondence, reports, dues renewal notices, and minutes. These materials date from 1967-99. This series is divided among eight of the Committee of 100 subcommittees. These subcommittees include Historic Preservation, Housing, Membership, Parks and Conservation, Planning and Urban Design, Transportation, Water Resources, and Zoning.
  - Historic Preservation: Correspondence, about the Baltimore Washington Parkway, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Historic Preservation: Correspondence, to James Speight from the Preservation subcommittee chairman expressing its opposition to the destruction of the property at 2129 Wyoming Avenue, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Historic Preservation: Correspondence, about 2801 Upton Street from the Upton Preservation League, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 3)